Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez

(+34)659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

ELLIS PhD Student in ML

GitHub: AdrianArnaiz LinkedIn: adrian-arnaiz-rodriguez WWW & Google Scholar

Research Interests I'm a '97 Spaniard currently focused on my thesis with a strong interest in Fairness, Causality and Graph theory. My current thesis addresses the ethical implications of ML decisions, including concepts such as privacy, transparency, accountability, reliability, autonomy and fairness, which urgently need to be taken into account in critical decision-making scenarios.

In my current thesis, we aim to tackle these challenges by leveraging graph theory and causal models to develop individual and group fair machine learning algorithms and metrics that enhance fairness, accountability, and transparency in algorithmic decision-making. In addition, we also delve into the long term effects and feedback loops of fair algorithms in sociotechnical scenarios.

EDUCATION

PhD Student / Fairness in ML

Dec 2021 - Present

ELLIS European lab. for Learning and Intelligent Systems - Alicante

- · Researching on Fairness in ML decision making leveraging graph theory, game theory and causality
- 6-months exchange at Max Plank Institute for Software Systems, Kaiserslautern, 2023
- Advised by Dr. Nuria Oliver (ELLIS), Dr. Manuel Gómez Rodríguez (MPI-SWS) and Dr. Francisco Escolano (UA)
- More info: [ELLIS] [Research Topic]

MSc in AI & Data Science

Jan 2020 — Jan 2021

GPA:9.7/10

- Universitat Oberta de Catalunya
- Thesis advised by Dr. Baris Kanber from University Collegue of London: Deep Convolutional Autoencoder for denoise T1 brain MRI

BSc in Computer Engeneering

Sep 2015 — Jun 2019

University of Burgos

GPA:8.9/10

• Evaluated both Bachelors and Thesis with Honors

• Evaluated both Masters and Thesis with Honors

- Extraordinary award: best student in the promotion.
- Thesis carried out in ADMIRABLE research lab: Use of biomarkers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Staff Jan 2020 — Aug 2021

ADMIRABLE and DATAHES research labs

University of Burgos, Spain

- European project [2019-1-ES01-KA204-065615] Self-Regulated Learning: SmartArt.
- Behavioural VR data analysis and Platform UBUMLaas
- Academic production shown in *Publications* section (Topic: Network Science)

AI Consultant Aug 2019 — Jan 2020

Ernst & Young firm

Madrid, Spain

• Building ML models for RPA integration: Intelligent Automation

Dec 2018 — Jun 2019 Research intern

ADMIRABLE research lab

University of Burgos, Spain

• Research intern with collaboration scholarship. Research in the project Use of biomarkers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson (BSc Thesis).

HONORS & AWARDS

Top 10% Reviewer ICML 2022 [Link]

International Conference on Machine Learning, July 2022

Selected in the top 10% best reviewers in ICML 2022 Conference.

FPU PhD Fellowship (Declined) - FPU20/03687

Spanish Government - Ministry of Universities, Sep 2021

Grants for pre-doctoral contracts in Spanish Universities.

Extraordinary Award of Bachelors in Computer Engineering

Council of the University of Burgos, Dec 2019

Best student of the Degree in Computer Engineering of the University of Burgos, of all the students graduated in 18/19.

Prototype Award OTRI (Information Transfer Office of Burgos University), Feb 2019

Project awarded: Use of bio-markers extracted from the voice for the detection of Parkinson.

Undergraduated Research Fellowship

University of Burgos, Dec 2018

Assistant research Fellowship in the Civil Engineering department of the University of Burgos, research group ADMIRABLE

Courses with honors Bachelor's and Master's

8 out of 10 MSc courses evaluated with honours, included Thesis. 10 BSc courses evaluated with honours, included Thesis.

Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez

(+34)659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

ELLIS PhD Student in ML

GitHub: AdrianArnaiz LinkedIn: adrian-arnaiz-rodriguez WWW & Google Scholar

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, José Luis Garrido-Labrador, and Alicia Olivares-Gil. "Computer Science doctoral research in Spain. A relational perspective". In: *Actas de la XIX Conferencia de la Asociación Española para la Inteligencia Artificial*. Universidad de Málaga. Málaga, 2021, pp. 667–672. ISBN: 978-84-09-30514-8. URL: https://caepia20-21.uma.es/inicio_files/caepia20-21-actas.pdf#page702.
- [2] José Luis Garrido-Labrador, José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, Virginia Ahedo, César Arnaiz-Rodríguez Adrián García-Osorio, José Ignacio Santos, and José Manuel Galán. "Network analysis of co-participation in thesis examination committees in an academic field in Spain". In: Abstract book of the 14th International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Industrial Management and XXIV Congreso de Ingeniería de Organización. Universidad Carlos III de Madrid. Burgos, 2020. URL: https://eventos.uc3m.es/_files/_event/_43190/_editorFiles/file/BookOfAbstracts10.pdf.

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Adrián Arnaiz-Rodríguez, Ahmed Begga, Francisco Escolano, and Nuria Oliver. "DiffWire: Inductive Graph Rewiring via the Lovász Bound". In: *arXiv preprint arXiv:2206.07369* (2022).
- [2] Alicia Olivares Gil, Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez, José Miguel Ramírez Sanz, José Luis Garrido Labrador, Virginia Ahedo García, César García Osorio, José Ignacio Santos Martín, José Manuel Galán Ordax, et al. "Mapping the scientific structure of organization and management of enterprises using complex networks". In: *International Journal of Production Management and Engineering* 10.1 (2022), pp. 65–76.
- [3] Esther Cubo, Adrian Arnaiz-Rodriguez, Álvar Arnaiz-González, José Francisco Díez-Pastor, Meredith Spindler, Adriana Cardozo, Alvaro Garcia-Bustillo, Zoltan Mari, and Bastiaan R Bloem. "Videoconferencing Software Options for Telemedicine: A Review for Movement Disorder Neurologists". In: *Frontiers in neurology* (2021), p. 1812.
- [4] María Consuelo Sáiz-Manzanares, Ismael Ramos Pérez, Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez, Sandra Rodríguez Arribas, Leandro Almeida, and Caroline Françoise Martin. "Analysis of the learning process through eye tracking technology and feature selection techniques". In: *Applied Sciences* 11.13 (2021), p. 6157.

TALKS

A Fairness perspective in algorithmic decision-making

[ELLIS Talks] Fairness in Machine Learning: From introduction to current approaches

University of Burgos (online), Mar 2022 University of Alicante, Jan 2022

Data processing in Advance Learning Technology S

Self-Regulated Learning in SmartArt Learning activities conference, Jul 2021

SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY SERVICES

Reviewer

[External reviewer] The Web Conference 2022 (WWW'22), ACM, New York.

[External reviewer] IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems 2022.

[External reviewer] ICML 2022 - International Conference on Machine Learning - Top 10%

[Program Committee member] ECML-PKDD 2022 - European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (x4 papers)

[External reviewer] Journal of Complexity 2022.

Scientific organization

Head of organization of ELLIS Doctoral Symposium 2022

Alicante, Sep 2022

Moderator of Qualcomm+ELLIS Reading Group Session about GNN+HCML

Online, Feb 2022

Round table: Pim de Haan, Carlos Castillo, Efstatios Gavves and Manuel Gómez Rodríguez

Virtual, Dec 2021

Volunteer at NeurIPS Workshop "Human-Centered AI"

virtual, Dec 202

Science communication

Head of ELLIS HCML Reading Group: guest sessions and round tables

bi-weekly sessions

Open Source software

Open source code from both BSc and MSc final projects

Occasional collaborator in Lightly AI PyTorch-based library for Self-Supervised Learing. Main contributor of *Lightly version 1.1.2* More open source codes in GitHub: applications, experiments and data analysis

Adrián Arnaiz Rodríguez

(+34)659540233 Alicante, Spain adrian@ellisalicante.org

ELLIS PhD Student in ML

GitHub: AdrianArnaiz LinkedIn: adrian-arnaiz-rodriguez WWW & Google Scholar

ACTIVITIES

Final stage II Premios Semilla Empresarial [Project]

3rd place in Innovation Contest Spin Up CyL by Junior Achievement Fundation Spain [Project]

Mar 2017

Jan 2017

SKILLS

Languages and libs Python, R, Tensorflow, PyTorch, PyGeometric

More interests Mathematical optimization, Mathematical Modeling, GNN, Reinforcement Learning

Communication Spanish (native), English (Fluent), German (A1)

Updated: 9th August 2022